<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An humble remonstrance to the right honourable, the Lords in the High Court of Parliament</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86868</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872397</idno>
  <idno type="VID">157113</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240943263</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3627</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E178_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3501</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872397</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99872397e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86868)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 157113)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 31:E178[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An humble remonstrance to the right honourable, the Lords in the High Court of Parliament</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Piinted [sic] and are to be sold by S. B.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1641]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to the petition of Sir Thomas Aston.</note>
                  <note>With royal coat of arms on title page.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect as filmed. "To the truly religious reader" is filmed as part of Thomason E.178[4], but is actually the epistle dedicatory to "Supersitio superstes", with imprint: "London: printed for P. W.. 1641.", Thomason E.178[5].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Aston, Thomas, --  Sir, 1600-1645. --  Humble petiton in behalfe of the county palatine of Chester.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">England and Wales. --  Parliament. --  House of Lords --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">Church of England. --  Bishops --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:157113:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:157113:1"/>
            <p>AN HVMBLE REMONSTRANCE TO The Right Honourable, the Lords in the High Court of <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>king's insignia</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON. Piinted, and are to be fold by <hi>S. B.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="appeal">
            <pb facs="tcp:157113:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:157113:2"/>
            <head>An Humble REMONSTRANCE To the right Honourable, the Lords in the High Court of Parliament.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Most Honourable Lords,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHereas the late Petitioner <hi>Sir. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Aston,</hi> Baronet, hath had accesse with his <hi>Petition,</hi> unto your presence, Entituled, <hi>An humble Petition in the behalfe of the County Palatine of Chester,</hi> which is (no doubt) discer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by your cleere judgments, to be as far from Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, as from Truth; which hath perplexed the minds of those honest men, whose names so great a Baronet hath much forgot himselfe, to use without their leave. Yet lest the Petitioner should glory in his prodigious policy<hi>:</hi> I humbly crave your Honors leave, to present to the world, a briefe view of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded projects, discerned by your Honours dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet wisdoms, far more cleerly. In which, Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> undertakes two things. First, to set up his own glory in his owne Petition. And secondly, to tryumph over us, and make us despicable in your eyes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Petitioner, Sir <hi>Thomas Aston,</hi> boasteth himselfe of the number, the honour, and the quality of the persons, subscribing to his <hi>Petition.</hi> Whereas testimony is ready to make it appeare, that amongst sevenscore in two parishes of the said County, 100 and 18 of that number (whose names he useth) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse
<pb facs="tcp:157113:3"/> they never atested to any such <hi>Petition,</hi> and that their hands are forged without theit consent, or knowledge: and for their honour, such persons as are Recusants, I know your Lordships doe well enough discerne their endeavours, not to be for, but against Protestant religion. And if dead men, mad-men and children be of quality fit for such an attestation; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold hands, and if that will not serve, see fained ones for them long since gone out of the land. But how forgetfull is the <hi>Baronet</hi> in his passionate Rhetoriks, alleadging, and traducing your honours, that your Lordships have approved thereof.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Sir <hi>Thomas Aston</hi> making his apologie to your honours, to prevent us from having favour before your Lordships eyes, doth declare, that those are se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious persons, who put a scandall upon the county, forgetting that himselfe had brought before your honours such names to his owne <hi>Petition,</hi> of whom many hundreds are ready (if occasion be) before your honours to protest against it: which S. <hi>Thomas</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe confesseth, is against the lawes of this land, and of your honourable Assembly: yet hath he troubled, and caused to be imprisoned, my self, &amp; some others, who protest before your honours, that wee had no hand at all in it. Yet I deny not, <hi>right honourable,</hi> but I have else-where writ against that order of Bishops which Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> calls honourable, and noble; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they are placed in the temporall seats of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall honour, and sit with the Nobility: whose ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour ought rathet to depend on their faithfull and constant preaching to their flock, and their Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to depend on heaven, being clothed with Christs righteousnesse, and preferring that above their <hi>linnen rotchets.</hi> The honour not of Magistracy, or Lordly
<pb facs="tcp:157113:3"/> nobility doth not so well become them as the name of shepheard. And whereas the <hi>Petitioner</hi> hath laid the burden of the Anti-petition upon our shoulders, I know your Honours doe well discerne his Ignoble and unbecomming forgeries, and calumnies therein expressed.</p>
            <p>And though I am ignorant whose burden I bore I take it contentedly, for Christ himselfe did so beare mine. Yet herein will your Honours be pleased to give me leave to side with the Anti-petitioner in this (rather, then with Sir <hi>Thomas Aston)</hi> That the proceedings of our Bishops, and Prelates, doe declare them to be the profest enemies of the Gospell: as may appeare by their Canons against the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell it selfe, their tyranny over the faithfull Preachers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, by their countenancing, and upholding the scurrilous and vild enemies against the same, and by their casting off of the lawes of temporall Magistrates; according to the institution therein contayned, which by many worthy men from time to time, hath bin lamented: amongst the rest I onely touch upon that saying of <hi>Henry Stalbridge,</hi> in the dayes of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. Who saith in his Epistle printed at <hi>Basill</hi> that not onely the bloudy Beare Wolfe of <hi>Rome,</hi> but other petty prollers; the prestigious Priests of <hi>Baal,</hi> especially the Bishops of England, doe roare like hungrie Lions, fret inwardly like angry Beares, and bite like cruell Wolfes; clustering together in corners like a swarme of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in a dunghill.</p>
            <p>Is their Institution <hi>Iure divine</hi> who deny the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution of Gods holy Sabbath soe to be, how can such discipline have any shadow of Divinity in it, this is to deny the word of God, and to set up the inventions of men, but blessed be God they cannot so delude our nation<hi>:</hi> for God be thanked, we well know that though their hierarchy is not <hi>Iure divino,</hi> yet the Sabbath of the Lord is holy and instituted of God himselfe. Were they one &amp; the same with the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching <hi>Presbiters</hi> according to the Scripture it would then be granted that they were Divine,</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:157113:4"/>
            <p> Or did they onely rule over the <hi>Presbyters</hi> by the willing assent, and consent of the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> it might be granted, that they were humane. But being that they assume, &amp; take to themselves the Lording power of their own wills, to tyrannize over Gods heritage; this is neither of God, nor of man. May your Honors then be pleased to consider, whether their <hi>institution</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Magde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Catalog. testium veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis, Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us a Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em, &amp;c.</note> be <hi>Ethnicall,</hi> or <hi>Diabolicall,</hi> or both: for to such their predominacy, the holy Ghost moves them not, the presbyters desire not: <hi>though Satan and evill spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits set them on, and draw them to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What their tyranny hath ever bin, may appeare in those many volumes written of their Acts, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents: <note place="margin">Bookes of Martyrs, French and English, <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bas Vsbergen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sis, St. Brides Revelations, Mathew Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, Alvarius Pelagius de Planetis Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiae, Arc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, Guiciar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine, Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus de Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mangiis, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Ecclesiae, Marselinus patavinus de fensoris pacis M.</hi> Tindall, &amp;c, <hi>M,</hi> Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners hunting <hi>of the Romish Fox, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> wherein their Lordly tyranny is declared at large, with their late <hi>Ex officio</hi> Oathes, Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications, and unjust proceedings, suspensions, &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisonments, and fines<hi>:</hi> their suppressing of the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Gospell, and the havock they from time to time have made of the flock of Iesus Christ. And that they have laboured to suppresse the true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; to bring in popery; may easily appeare, in their crying downe and silencing the godly, painfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of Jesus Christ, terming them Puritans, factious men, &amp;c. In their perverting the lawes of God, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stablishing their owne Canons and inventions, their taking of rewards, and admitting unable men into Ecclesiasticall Offices; even such, whose filthinesse, Idlenesse, and Riot, made them live, more like Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures, then Pastors: wasting their pretious time in drinking, revelling, dancing, feasting, tabling, bouling, piping, carding, dicing<hi>:</hi> and having furfetted, &amp; being drunke, quarrell, fight, &amp; cause tumults, and prophane
<pb facs="tcp:157113:4"/> the name of God by oathes, and curses, and somtimes even from the embracements of their Harlots, come into the Church to performe Ecclesiasticall duties, And how have they laboured in the bringing in of popish <hi>Ceremonies, Crucifixes, Altars,</hi> and Images. Tapers, &amp;c. But all this while, how hath preaching bin neglected in many darke corners of the Land.</p>
            <p>Now, may it please your Honours, what the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition is, wherewith Sir <hi>Thomas Aston</hi> is so offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, I being altogether ignorant of, J therefore passe it over, onely what he saith of it. May your Lordships be pleased, to give me leave to returne his own words into his owne bosome, before your Honours; whose owne expressions, will unmaske the horrible abuses in his owne proceedings, so fully, that J shall passe it over, onely leaving the consideration thereof; to your Lordships discretion<hi>:</hi> beseeching Almighty God to inspire your great Counsels, with all wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from above, with happy successe to your joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meeting; to the glory of God, and the comfort of us all, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:157113:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:157113:5"/>
            <head>To the truly Religious Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether Religion be a Vertue, or the Mother, and bond of all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, I will not now dispute. This I am sure of, that it happens to it, as unto Divine and Morall vertues, to be attended with two extreames, the one on the left hand, the other on the right; the one called <hi>Prophanenesse,</hi> the other <hi>Superstition:</hi> the one whereof is the <hi>defect,</hi> the other the <hi>excesse</hi> of Religion. That both of these are enemies to Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and odious to God, there is no question; but whether most, is yet uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, which we shall then resolve, when we have manifested these three things, 1. What Superstition is. 2. How common. 3. How great a sin it is.</p>
            <p>For the first; Superstition, in the generall, is nothing else but the excesse <note place="margin">1. <hi>What Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstition is.</hi> Superstitio est superstuus timor superstantium, 1. cal<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stium qu<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> supra nos stant. Minsh. Dict.</note> of Religion, or rather Religion run out of the wits, <hi>q. d.</hi> by a superfluous and slavish feare of the Deitie. Hence it is fitly by the Greekes, called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Act.</hi> 25.19. a feare of the Deitie; And of the <hi>Athenians</hi> (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise prophane enough) the Apostle sayes, he did perceive them to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, too superstitious, too fearefull of the <hi>Daimons,</hi> whom they ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly did worship, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.22. For the conscience of such men being terrified by its owne guiltinesse and prophanenesse, puts them upon such wayes to please their God, and make him propitious, as best would please themselves, were they in his steed. And from hence proceeds that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Col.</hi> 2.23. that will-worship, whereby men take upon them to prescribe to God, how he shall be served; every man according to his owne fancie, and imagination of God. From whence it doth appeare, that superstition is a sin <note place="margin">Aquin 22 q. 92. ar. 2.</note> against the second Commandement, and is rather a species of Idolatry, than the Genus of it, as the great Schooleman seemes to make it: For Idolatry is two wayes committed, either by worshipping a false God, or the true God in a false manner: The first of these is prohibited in the first Commandement, the other in the second; The first was the sinne of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> the other was the sinne of the <hi>Israelites,</hi> in the time of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> who worshipped the true God, in the Image of a golden Calfe; and the sinne of all those who worship God, with the inventions and traditions of men. Now when I say, that Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstition <note place="margin">Ibid. ar. I. c.</note> is the excesse of Religion, we may not so take it, as if a man could properly be too religious, or give God more than is due to him, or he deserves: but in that a man gives that to God as part of worship, which he doth not require, which is indeed to give him lesse. For the affirmative part of the fourth Commandement being this, That God must bee worshipped with his
<pb facs="tcp:157113:6"/> owne prescribed worship; hee that shall now devise a way of worship of his owne, and tender this to God, to make him propitious (fearing that that is prescribed, will not doe it sufficiently) this is that which stiles him supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious. And this is that we call Superstition.</p>
            <p>For the second thing propounded, How common a sin this Superstition is, <note place="margin">How com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon a sinne Superstition <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> as it doth appeare by instances of all times and places; So also by the frequent and strict prohibitions given against it. The second Commandement is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore propounded negatively, to imply, that men are apter to adde, (which is Superstition, as we said) than to detract from the prescribed Rules of worship (which is prophanenesse.) Certaine it is indeed, that Prophannesse and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition have almost divided the world betweene them (there being few that find, or keepe the golden Meane of Religion) but whether of them hath the greator share is yet uncertaine. The difficulty of deciding this doubt, is thus augmented; That the same parties (being not truly Religions) are often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times both prophane and superstitious. Prophane without, in common life, and superstitious within the Church, when they come to tender their devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Nay the Scripture gives us instances enough, and too many of those kind of men, who were most notoriously prophane and wicked, and yet exceeded in their formalities, and ceremoniall services of God, <hi>Isa.</hi> 1. <hi>Jer.</hi> 7. <hi>Psal.</hi> 50. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And however prophannesse in the very worship of God bee a common vice, and men be too propense unto it; yet, if I mistake not, men are more inclined to be superstitions in their worship, than prophane, and that for these reasons.</p>
            <p>First, Atheisme, which is the Mother of prophannesse, is not so common; few there be that say, There is no God; or if they say it, that really beleeve it. For this is a naturall principle surviving the Fall of man, <hi>[That there is a God]</hi> upon which depends this next conclusion, <hi>[That this God must be worshipped]</hi> and that with Reverence; But there is no light left in man, How God will be worshipped, at least for the externall part; whereas there are some reliques of moralitie left, to keepe men from extreme prophannesse. Hereupon it comes to passe, that men are apt to thinke, that God is like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, to be pleased best, with free-will-offerings of their owne, that is, with will-worship, and voluntarie Humilitie, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 18. and that the highest, or rather the lowest expressions of Devotion are fittest for him: And thus (wanting light) they find out many inventions, to serve God withall, which is nothing else but <hi>Superstition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, because men are naturally proud, and conceited of their owne wisedome, even to prescribe in the service of God. Hence wee may observe, that when the Apostle speakes of Will-worship and Superstition, he commonly intimates the cause and originall thereof, to bee the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the wisedome of the flesh. That Humilitie, or demission of mind, that was pleaded for wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipping of Angels, using them as Mediators to God, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 18. was the
<pb facs="tcp:157113:6"/> devise of some, <hi>[That were vainly puffed up in their fleshly mind.]</hi> And so in the following verses, those Traditions, <hi>[Touch not, tast not, handle not]</hi> had the same originall <hi>[which things have a shew of wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> &amp;c.] The like is to be observed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.22.23. The Gentiles when they changed the glory of God, into Images of all sorts, thought themselves very wise: for so hee sayes, <hi>[professing themselves wise, they became fooles.]</hi> The Israelites also, when they chose them places, and trees to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship God in, and under them (contrary to expresse command of God) wanted not pretence of reason for what they did, <hi>Hos.</hi> 4.13. <hi>[They Sacrifise upon the tops of the Mountaines, and burne Incense upon the Hills, under the Oake, the Poplar tree, and the Elme, because the shadow thereof is good, &amp;c.]</hi> Good in regard of Divine presence, more there than else-where: Good in regard of more Holinesse, as consecrated to such a Deitie: Good last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to stirre up more devotion, for the former reasons, <hi>viz.</hi> the consideration of Divine presence, and more Holinesse there than in other places. Now, this proud conceited wisedome, keepes men so farre from being prophane in the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, that it rather precipitates them into the other extreme, and that is <hi>Superstition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, that men may <hi>Supererogate</hi> with God is a naturall piece of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie, borne and bred up in the hearts of all men; by which men thinke either to merit of God, if lesse grossely vitious, or at least, to set off with him, and to quit the score of former arreares, by voluntary and uncommanded services. If they find they faile and come short in some thing commanded, they will overdoe, in some other thing not commanded, and so they take it, that God is satisfied. Now to foster and favour this opinion, the performance of requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red services will not serve the turne. For no man can dreame to merit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, or satisfie a debt, by a necessary and enjoyned performance; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that he may supererogate in both, hee must devise and undertake some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing not commanded. Hence were and are, those counsels of perfection, of the old Papists, the Pharisees; and the New Pharisees, the Papists: Wee heare one of them bragging; I thanke God, I pay Tithes of all I doe possesse, that was but his dutie: but more than that, I fast twice a weeke, which God never required of him: implying, that either God was beholden to him, or at least, he was not beholden to God, or any wayes behind-hand with him, though he had failed in other things; for in doing more than was commanded, he had made amends for what he had offended. Of this mind it seemes were their Predecessors, <hi>Isay</hi> 58. who durst expostulate with God, as not observing their devotions: <hi>[Wherefore have we fasted, and thou regardest it not?]</hi> They could not be so senslesse, as not to see and know themselves to be faultie enough, (as God charges them presently upon it) but had they not thought, the satisfaction made by Fasting more than was requirea, they had not made
<pb facs="tcp:157113:7"/> that bold and sawcie expostulation with God. It is the naturall fashion of hypocrites, to ply God with ceremonials, for neglect of morals: and to make amends (as they thinke) for breach of Gods commands, by substitution of their owne superstitious Traditions. And in this notion wee may say, that superstition springs from the ground of prophanenesse: none commonly being more ceremonious (that is superstitious) than they that are most prophane. For knowing themselves indebted for morall transgressions, they labour to compensate God with Ceremonials, either of his commanding, or of their own devising. Guiltinesse (as I said) drives them to doe something to appease an angry, and by prophannesse provoked God; Duties commanded by God, when best performed, are but duties, and therefore pay no former debts: Onely Counsels of perfection, or devises of higher Devotion, seeme to su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pererrogate, and this is <hi>Superstition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, because there is more credit and applause from men, not onely more than can be looked for, in prophannesse (which is lyable to dishonour, and just hatred) but more than can be gotten, by doing things commanded. To doe duties commanded by God, (at least for the outward act) is vulgar, and common to every Professour of Religion: but hee that transcends com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and worships God, with voluntary worship, with greatest humilitie, and abjection of himselfe, this is the Saint of hypocrites, and the Angell of ignorant men. This is easily observable, that those that were exactest in ceremonials (whether Gods, or their owne, but rather their owne) though guilty often in morals, carryed away the credit of the world from them that were more exact in morals, and equally exact in Ceremonials of Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribing. <hi>Zacharie</hi> and <hi>Eliz.</hi> that walked in all the Commandements, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and statutes of the Lord without rebuke, were not in halfe that repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, that the Pharisees were, who did exceed in observation of their owne Traditions. Nay, our blessed Sauiour himselfe, though most exact in all commands of God, could not winne so much credit and applause as the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risees had in those times. And the Pharisees had no better way (as they thought) to suppresse the growing fame of him and his Disciples, than to lay upon them this imputation of want of Devotion, in not observing the Traditions of the Elders.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, because as Ceremonials are easier to doe than morals, so those Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonials which themselves invented, they can more easily, and more exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performe, than those of Gods prescribing. How easie a thing it was, to Sacrifice a beast, how hard to mortifie a lust? How easie a thing it was to wash their hands, and pots, and cups, and dishes; How hard to wash their hearts from rapine and extortion? How easie a thing it is to bow the body with severall Postures and gesticulations, how hard to bend the soule to Gods commands? Now the truth is, Superstition, though it seeme a busie,
<pb facs="tcp:157113:7"/> yet it is but a lazie thing. Like some lither and idle servants, who are very quick about lesser matters, but remisse enough in businesses of greater waight or labour. Nay, therefore double diligent in lesser, that they may exempt themselves from harder works: Just so it is, with Superstitious hypocrites, they sometimes tire themselves, and weary God, with ritualls, that they may slip their necks from harder services. Besides, there is another thing in it. Their owne Devises, they can, and know they can, exactly performe; but things of Gods prescription, are very hard, if not for matter, yet for manner to be performed. Hence they find just cause to be humbled in their best per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances of Gods commands, as failing and falling short of what was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, but they find cause to applaud themselves, and to glory in their owne devised services, because they have exactly performed them.</p>
            <p>Lastly, because the most wicked and profane, desire not so to seeme, but find out figg-leaves to cover their profanenesse. <hi>Herod,</hi> though he intended mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, pretended worship unto Christ. <hi>Iezabel</hi> that meant to swallow down <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boths</hi> Vineyard, proclames a Fast. The Pharisees that devoured widowes houses, did it with a pretence of long prayers. Now the more seemingly devout men are at Church, the lesse they are suspected to be wicked at home, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. Who would imagine to finde a widowes house, in the bowells of a long praying Pharisee? or to meet with rapine and extortion, in a washed and scoured dish? Who would think, that a man that bowes constantly, devoutly, at the Name of Jesus, would commonly sweare by the name of God, or Christ? Who would looke to find those, that bowe so much, so oft before the Altar, so stiffe to yeeld obedience to the morall cōmands of God? In a word, to find men, who are religious even to Superstition, to be profane even to Admiration? Ʋp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all these reasons, and perhaps more, it may appeare, that men are more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to Superstition, than to profanenesse; and consequently, that profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse is not so common, as Superstition.</p>
            <p>And now wee come to the third, How great a sinne Superstition is; For though it be true, that <hi>profanenesse</hi> is an odious sinne, and so esteemed by <note place="margin">How great a sinne Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition is.</note> men; yet sure it is, that <hi>Superstition</hi> is most abominable to God, notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>standing those many specious <hi>pretences</hi> that it hath, of singular and speciall <hi>Devotion;</hi> which we shall thus demonstrate.</p>
            <p>First, it derogates from the infinite wisedom of God, as if he were not wise enough to prescribe his own worship: we said before, that <hi>Superstition</hi> wants not shewes of wisedom, to make it plausible with men, and (as they thinke) well pleasing to God: Now for foolish man, to make himselfe wiser than God, in matter of his owne worship, as it proceeds from intollerable pride and presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, so it cannot choose but be abominable to God. No King, no Father, no Master on earth, would suffer such insolence from their inferiours, that they should take upon them to prescribe their manner of service; and shall God?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:157113:8"/>
            <p> Secondly, it detracts not onely from the perfection and truth of Scriptures by addition to the Rule of worship, but it belyes both the Scripture, and God himselfe, making that his command, and a part of worship, which is the fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and device of man. The false, Prophets were of old charged with forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, for saying, Thus saith the Lord when the Lord hath not spoken it. And of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> who was superstitious in the service of God, thus it is said; <hi>[Ephraim compasses me about with lyes,</hi> Hos. 12.1.] To this purpose is that of <hi>Solomon.</hi> Pro. 30. 6. <hi>[Add not thou unto his words, lest hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them, and thou be found a lyar,]</hi> for putting that upon God, as if it were his word, which is thine own invention. As not to beleeve what God testifies, is to make him a lyar, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 10. So to make him say, what he sayes not, is also to put upon him a lye. Now we know how haynous a crime it is, to give the lye to a man, at least our Superiour: How great a sinne then is it to put the lye upon the God of truth?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, whereas men pretend they doe it out of their great respects and love of God, as thinking nothing too deare, too much for God; the truth is, it proceeds from hatred of God: This is evident in the second commandement, where those that keepe Gods Commandements, that is, his prescriptions of worship, according to the second commandement, are said to love him, and keepe his commandements. And on the contrary, they that break his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, either by defect, or by additions of their owne, are said to hate him: <hi>[Visiting the sinnes, &amp;c. upon them that hate me:]</hi> Now there is nothing more odious, to God or men, than hatred masked under the pretences of love.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it is Idolatry, not onely against the second commandement, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipping God in a false manner, but even against the first commandement, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther negatively, not having the true God for our God; or positively, setting up another God, in his steed. First, the first commandement requires, not onely that we have no other God, but also, that wee have the true God for our God. But hee that worships God in a false manner, hath not the true God for his God, nor doth he worship him. This is evident in 2 <hi>King.</hi> 17.32.34. In the one verse it is said; They feared or served the Lord, that is, they intended so to doe; but in the other, it is said, They feared not the Lord; and the reason <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh</hi> 4 22 <hi>You worship, you know not what.</hi>
               </note> is rendred, because they did not serve him according to the Law, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, which the Lord commanded the sonnes of <hi>Iacob,</hi> &amp;c. For the other, that the Superstitious worshipper, sets up another God in the steed of the true God, will thus appeare; because he sets up himselfe in the steed of God; and in serving God, hee serves himselfe. This is easily collected from that speech of God himselfe, <hi>Zach</hi> 7.5. <hi>[When you fasted and mourned, in the fifth and seventh moneth, as now these seventy yeares; did you fast at all to me, I say, to me? when you eat and drank, did you not eat to your selves and drink to your selves?]</hi> As if he should say, you fasted to
<pb facs="tcp:157113:8"/> your selves, as well as you did eat and drink to your selves. Those Fasts I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired not, you devised them of your owne heads, and observed them, as your owne Traditions, and so in worshipping me, you worshipped your selves. And this was in effect, to set up your selves as God. As if a Subject or Servant shall prescribe Lawes, how they will serve their King or Master; is not this to set up themselves, in steed of their King and Master? So doe all superstiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous persons; they pull downe God out of his Throne, and place themselves therein, and under pretence of worshipping God, they worship themselves, which is most grosse Idolatry, against the first commandement.</p>
            <p>Lastly, it is the worst and highest degree of Idolatry, not onely the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipping of an Idoll, but it is the worshipping of the Devill, Gods greatest ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, insteed of God, placing him in the Throne of God. This is evident by the Scriptures; in many instances. The Gentiles first, intended no doubt to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer sacrifices to the true God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 21. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.23 Yet the Apostle sayes expresly, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 20. The things which the Gentiles offer, they offer to Devils and not to God. <hi>Aaron</hi> and the Israelites, intended also to worship the true God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.5. These be thy Gods, O <hi>Israel,</hi> which brought thee out of Egypt: Yet <hi>Levit.</hi> 17.7. they are forbidden to sacrifise any more (as they had done) to Devils. The 10 Tribes had the same good intentions, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12.28. Yet 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11.15. It is said of <hi>Ieroboam. [He ordained him Priests—for the Devils, and for the calves which he made.]</hi> Because they worshipped the true God, in a false manner, therefore they are said to worship the Devill insteed of God. In a word, The Papists, that worship God, in Images of gold, silver, brasse, stone, and wood, &amp;c. suppose that they worship the true God; but S. <hi>Iohn</hi> sayes, they worship Devils. <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.20. By all which hath binsaid, it now appeares, that however <hi>Superstition</hi> makes a faire shew of honouring God, and is of high esteeme with men; yet it is an hainous sinne, and most justly, for the former reasons, most abominable to God.</p>
            <p>To apply this a little to our present purpose. This Age of ours is profane enough, there is no question to be made of that. It cannot also be denyed, but <hi>profanenesse</hi> began to creepe apace upon the service of God; But I dare say, that <hi>Superstition,</hi> like a gangrene, hath crept further in a fewe yeares, than <hi>profanenesse</hi> did in many, and had it not beene maturely checked, it might, for ought I know, by this time have carried us neere to <hi>Rome.</hi> Amongst other particulars, wherein <hi>Superstition</hi> began to revive, some are here presented to thy view (good Reader) as leaders of the rest. Apparent it is, that some men began to put so much <hi>holinesse</hi> in Churches, and things thereto belonging, that they had almost lost all <hi>holinesse</hi> in themselves: and the <hi>holinesse</hi> of <hi>places</hi> had wellnigh eat up all the <hi>holinesse</hi> of <hi>Times,</hi> unlesse they were <hi>Times</hi> of mens devising. For first, is it not evident, that the <hi>Holy dayes</hi> so called, had thrust out almost the <hi>holinesse</hi> of the <hi>Lords Day,</hi> or gotten to themselves
<pb facs="tcp:157113:9"/> equall honour with it? The Holy dayes of Saints were as strictly pressed to be observed, and by themselves observed, with more devotion, with more solemne services, than the Lords Day; On them men might not work, in their honest callings, but presently they were presented; On this, (the Lords Day) they gave them liberty, without sinne, not onely to labour, but to play, and that such playes, as scarce beseeme a common, much lesse, an <hi>Holy day.</hi> For the <hi>places</hi> also of humane consecration, how <hi>sacred</hi> and holy were they esteemed, not onely in their publick use, but <hi>extra usum.</hi> No vessell, no burden, might passe through them, no businesse saecular might be done in them; whereas the <hi>Lords Day</hi> was counted <hi>holy,</hi> no longer than the <hi>publick Service</hi> lasted. From the <hi>Altar</hi> to the <hi>Bell-ropes,</hi> all were Sacred; no comming in to the Church, no going out, without uncovering, adoration, prostration, once, twice, thrice, forward, backward; and he that would not doe so, was held, little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than profane. The very <hi>Churchyards</hi> were growne so holy, that if a <hi>beast</hi> did but touch them, they were held by some profaned. Hence those <hi>Holy Articles,</hi> given to enquire, whether any kinde of cattell were suffered to feed therein. Such is the spreading nature of <hi>Superstition,</hi> that though the <hi>Churchyard</hi> bounds be known, yet <hi>Superstition</hi> once gotten into the Church, knowes no limits. I will make bold to borrow the words of another, altering onely the Subject whereof he spake, to this in hand, and adding some few words besides. <hi>[Of the two great enemies of Gods holy worship, although</hi> profanenesse, <hi>in it selfe, be the more offensive; yet</hi> Superstition <hi>is more</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hist of Sab. epist. d<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d.</note>
               <hi>spreading, and more quick of growth. In such a Church as this, so set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, in a constant practise of Religious offices, and so confirmed by godly</hi> Canons, <hi>for the performance of the same there was no feare, that ever the publick worship of God would have beene over-runne by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane neglect of any pious reverence, then required. Rather the danger was, lest by the violent torrent of some mens affections, it might have be<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne overflowne by those Superstitions, wherewith, in imitation of the Iewes, (or Papists) they began to charge it: and thereby made it, as burdensome to their brethren, as was the ceremoniall Law to the Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, by the Law of</hi> Moses. <hi>Nor know wee, where they would have stayed, had not the Honourable Parliament now assembled, been pleased, out of a tender care of the worship of God, and safety of Religion, to give a check to their proceedings.]</hi> But I may not enlarge my Epistle too farre, lest my Porch grow too bigg for my house. I leave what ever hath, or shall be said, to the candide censure of the godly and judicious Reader.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>